<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: anima grass -->
  <Plant_GrassAnima.label>grama anima</Plant_GrassAnima.label>
  <!-- EN: A grass infused with luminous microorganisms. Tribal peoples find that anima grass grows around the base of an anima tree as they meditate. It seems to reflect some kind of strengthening of the tree's psychic power.\n\nOffworld scientists have tried to study the phenomenon, but the grass degenerates into normal plant matter when observed too closely.\n\nAnimals refuse eat anima grass. Tribal stories say this is done out of respect and fear. -->
  <Plant_GrassAnima.description>Uma grama infundida com microorganismos luminosos. Os povos tribais descobrem que a grama anima cresce em torno da base de uma árvore anima enquanto meditam. Parece refletir algum tipo de fortalecimento do poder psíquico da árvore.\n\nOs cientistas do mundo todo tentaram estudar o fenômeno, mas a grama degenera em matéria vegetal normal quando observada com muita atenção.\n\nOs animais recusam a comer grama anima. Histórias tribais dizem que isso é feito por respeito e medo.</Plant_GrassAnima.description>
  
  <!-- EN: anima tree -->
  <Plant_TreeAnima.label>árvore anima</Plant_TreeAnima.label>
  <!-- EN: A rare tree with warm, skin-smooth bark and long iridescent leaves. Infused with bioluminescent micro-organisms, anima trees develop a unique form of psychic symbiosis with surrounding lifeforms, allowing them to grow in a wide variety of biomes.\n\nIf a person (psycaster or not) meditates near an anima tree, it will grow anima grass around its base. Once enough grass is grown, it becomes possible to carry out a psychic linking ritual with the tree and upgrade a person's psychic powers. Only tribal peoples know the secret of this ritual. Tribal psycasters are also able to draw psyfocus from anima trees while meditating to them.\n\nAnima trees' psychic properties are weakened if artificial structures are placed nearby. They refuse to be caged or studied, and must remain part of nature.\n\nMost tribes believe that anima trees are not simply trees, but are rather the physical extremities of a single world spirit. -->
  <Plant_TreeAnima.description>Uma árvore rara, com uma casca morna e macia, e folhas longas e iridescentes. Infundidas com microrganismos bioluminescentes, as árvores anima desenvolvem uma forma única de simbiose psíquica com as formas de vida circundantes, permitindo que elas cresçam em uma ampla variedade de biomas.\n\nSe uma pessoa (psycaster ou não) medita perto de uma árvore anima, ela irá crescer grama anima em torno de sua base. Uma vez cultivada grama suficiente, torna-se possível realizar um ritual de ligação psíquica com a árvore e aprimorar os poderes psíquicos de uma pessoa. Somente os povos tribais conhecem o segredo desse ritual. Psycasters tribais também são capazes de extrair psyfocus das árvores anima enquanto meditam para elas.\n\nAs propriedades psíquicas das árvores anima são enfraquecidas se estruturas artificiais forem colocadas nas proximidades. Elas se recusam a serem enjauladas ou estudadas e devem permanecer parte da natureza.\n\nA maioria das tribos acreditam que as árvores anima não são simplesmente árvores, mas são as extremidades físicas de um único espírito do mundo.</Plant_TreeAnima.description>
  <!-- EN: About: Anima tree linking -->
  <Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompPsylinkable.enoughPlantsLetterLabel>Sobre: Ligação com árvore anima</Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompPsylinkable.enoughPlantsLetterLabel>
  <!-- EN: The anima tree now has {0} anima grass around it. This is enough for a tribal person to begin their first linking ritual!\n\nThe linking ritual gives a level of psylink and the ability to use psychic powers. Upgrading to a higher level requires more grass at each level.\n\nThe anima grass requirements for linking rituals to upgrade psycasters are:\n\n{1}\n\nNote: Only those with the nature focus type can meditate to or link with anima trees. You can see a person’s focus types by looking at their info card with the ‘i’ button. -->
  <Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompPsylinkable.enoughPlantsLetterText>A árvore da anima agora tem {0} grama anima ao seu redor. Isso é suficiente para uma pessoa tribal iniciar seu primeiro ritual de ligação!\n\nO ritual de ligação fornece um nível de psylink e a capacidade de usar poderes psíquicos. A atualização para um nível mais alto exige mais grama a cada nível.\n\nOs requisitos da grama anima para rituais de vinculação para atualizar psycasters são:\n\n{1}\n\nNota: Somente aqueles com o tipo de foco da natureza podem meditar ou se vincular com árvores anima. Você pode ver os tipos de foco de uma pessoa observando o cartão de informações com o botão 'i'.</Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompPsylinkable.enoughPlantsLetterText>
  <!-- EN: The anima tree has died and emitted a disturbing psychic scream. -->
  <Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompGiveThoughtToAllMapPawnsOnDestroy.message>A árvore da anima morreu e emitiu um grito psíquico perturbador.</Plant_TreeAnima.comps.CompGiveThoughtToAllMapPawnsOnDestroy.message>
  
</LanguageData>