<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: baseliner -->
  <Baseliner.label>padrão</Baseliner.label>
  <!-- EN: A naturally-evolved human with no major significant genetic modifications. -->
  <Baseliner.description>Um humano evoluído naturalmente sem grandes modificações genéticas significativas.</Baseliner.description>
  
  <!-- EN: dirtmole -->
  <Dirtmole.label>cavaterra</Dirtmole.label>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, they thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are extremely capable at digging or mining tasks. In the open, however, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance.\n\nAfter the first tunnel colonies failed due to the stress of confinement, colonization agencies began genetically altering colonists to live without open space or sunlight. This xenotype is known colloquially as the dirtmoles. Today, dirtmoles have expanded out of their original tunnel homes and rule many confined spaces in the anthrosphere. They can be found in deep mines, cramped low-tech spacecraft, and teeming by the billions in the dark underlayers of countless urbworlds. -->
  <Dirtmole.description>Com pele cinzenta adaptada a luz artificial, eles prosperam em espaços apertados e escuros onde combates e viagens acontecem em distâncias curtas. Eles são extremamente hábeis em tarefas de escavação ou mineração. Ao ar livre, no entanto, eles sofrem de sensibilidade à luz, velocidade lenta e visão deficiente à distância.\n\nDepois que as primeiras colônias de túneis falharam devido ao estresse do confinamento, as agências de colonização começaram a alterar geneticamente os colonos para viver sem espaço aberto ou luz solar. Este xenótipo é conhecido coloquialmente como cavaterra. Hoje, os cavaterra se expandiram de suas casas de túnel originais e governam muitos espaços confinados na antroposfera. Eles podem ser encontrados em minas profundas, naves espaciais de baixa tecnologia apertadas e fervilhando aos bilhões nas camadas escuras de inúmeros mundos urbanos.</Dirtmole.description>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, dirtmoles thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are naturals at digging and navigating complex tunnel structures. In the open, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance. -->
  <Dirtmole.descriptionShort>Com a pele cinzenta adaptada à luz artificial, os cavaterra prosperam em espaços apertados e escuros, onde combates e viagens acontecem em distâncias curtas. Eles naturalmente sabem cavar e navegar em estruturas complexas de túneis. Ao ar livre, eles sofrem de sensibilidade à luz, baixa velocidade e baixa visão à distância.</Dirtmole.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: genie -->
  <Genie.label>gênio</Genie.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies' delicate bones and natural aptitude with machines allow them to manipulate devices with remarkable precision. They are emotionally cold and can follow orders where others might panic. However, they are fragile, and their amplified nerve impulses make them easy to debilitate with relatively little pain. With so much of their brains dedicated to analyzing machines, they lack the neural hardware to analyze emotions, so they sometimes come off as socially inept. Their dead calm makes it even harder for them to relate to what they see as madly-hotheaded baseliner humans.\n\nGenies were engineered thousands of years ago by a long-disbanded space navy to hold engineering positions on large starships. Today, genies still serve as engineers in great cities and fleets, but many can also be found working as lawyers, pilots, and musicians. -->
  <Genie.description>Projetados para serem engenheiros, os ossos delicados e a aptidão natural dos gênios com máquinas permite-os manipular dispositivos com notável precisão. Eles são emocionalmente frios e podem seguir ordens onde outros podem entrar em pânico. Contudo, eles são frágeis, e seus impulsos nervosos amplificados os tornam fáceis de debilitar com relativamente pouca dor. Com tanto de seus cérebros dedicados a analisar máquinas, eles carecem do hardware neural para analisar emoções, então às vezes parecem socialmente ineptos. Sua calma mortal torna ainda mais difícil para eles se relacionarem com o que eles veem como seres humanos padrão loucos e de cabeça-quente.\n\nGênios foram projetados há milhares de anos por uma marinha espacial há muito dissolvida para ocuparem posições de engenharia em grandes naves estelares. Hoje, gênios ainda atuam como engenheiros em grandes cidades e frotas, mas muitos também podem ser encontrados trabalhando como advogados, pilotos e músicos.</Genie.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies have natural aptitude with machines, and are emotionally cold and calm. They are also fragile and vulnerable to pain. Focused on machines, they often come off as socially inept. -->
  <Genie.descriptionShort>Projetados para serem engenheiros, os gênios têm aptidão natural com máquinas e são emocionalmente frios e calmos. Eles também são frágeis e vulneráveis à dor. Focados em máquinas, eles muitas vezes parecem socialmente ineptos.</Genie.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: highmate -->
  <Highmate.label>alto companheiro</Highmate.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence.\n\nOn a few wealthy worlds, highmate xenogerms are commercially available and some people become highmates as a sort of career. However, many societies find them abhorrent, either because they distract people from forming natural families, or because they are humans shaped to serve the pleasures of another. On such worlds they are either reserved as playthings of the powerful, or banned entirely. This particular line of highmate fits the fashions of classical Novaroma, but many other variants exist. -->
  <Highmate.description>Companheiros e concubinas projetados com uma capacidade única de se relacionar psiquicamente com um companheiro, os alto companheiros são empáticos, bonitos, alegres e talentosos em questões sociais. Eles também são ineptos em tarefas manuais, fisicamente fracos e mentalmente incapazes de violência.\n\nEm alguns mundos ricos, xenogerminadores de alto companheiros estão disponíveis comercialmente e algumas pessoas se tornam alto companheiros como uma espécie de carreira. No entanto, muitas sociedades os consideram abomináveis, seja porque distraem as pessoas de formar famílias naturais, seja porque são humanos moldados para servir aos prazeres de outros. Em tais mundos, eles são reservados como brinquedos dos poderosos ou totalmente banidos. Esta linha particular de alto companheiros se encaixa na moda clássica de Novaroma, mas existem muitas outras variantes.</Highmate.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence. -->
  <Highmate.descriptionShort>Companheiros e concubinas projetados com uma capacidade única de se relacionar psiquicamente com um companheiro, os alto companheiros são empáticos, bonitos, alegres e talentosos em questões sociais. Eles também são ineptos em tarefas manuais, fisicamente fracos e mentalmente incapazes de violência.</Highmate.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: hussar -->
  <Hussar.label>hussardo</Hussar.label>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice, which also makes them less likely to rebel against their commanders.\n\nWhile hussars' emotions make them dangerous in combat, they can't relate to baseliner humans. They are famous for their blood-red eyes and "hussar stare", a dead expression that unsettles many people. Their lack of expression and burning aggressive nature has led to many violent misunderstandings.\n\nIn most societies where they live, hussars are kept separated from the rest of the population. Hussars are single-purpose tools - and they generally aren't bothered by the fact. -->
  <Hussar.description>Os hussardos são soldados projetados. Eles lutam agressivamente e com precisão, curam-se rapidamente, prosperam em temperaturas extremas e ingerem drogas militares livremente. Eles têm uma dependência genética em suco turbo, o que também os torna menos propensos a se rebelar contra seus comandantes.\n\nEmbora as emoções dos hussardos os tornem perigosos em combate, eles não podem se relacionar com humanos padrão. Eles são famosos por seus olhos vermelho-sangue e "olhar hussardo", uma expressão morta que inquieta muitas pessoas. Sua falta de expressão e natureza agressiva e ardente levaram a muitos mal-entendidos violentos.\n\nNa maioria das sociedades em que vivem, os hussardos são mantidos separados do resto da população. Os hussardos são ferramentas de propósito único - e geralmente não se incomodam com o fato.</Hussar.description>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice. -->
  <Hussar.descriptionShort>Os hussardos são soldados projetados. Eles lutam agressivamente e com precisão, curam-se rapidamente, prosperam em temperaturas extremas e ingerem drogas militares livremente. Eles têm uma dependência genética em suco turbo.</Hussar.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: impid -->
  <Impid.label>diabrete</Impid.label>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impid cultures live on many rimworlds and dry deathworlds. Impids are extremely fast-moving, easily tolerate high temperatures, and can spew fire from their mouths. Though they are masters on the sand, impids struggle in other environments. They are terrible with farming. They fight well at range, but in close combat their physical weakness becomes apparent.\n\nOutlanders call them dustrunners because of their speed over open terrain and resistance to heat. Some tribes call them devils because of their horns and because they burn their enemies. Impid tribes' combat tactics usually center on rapid-approach incendiary attacks using both handheld fire weapons and their fire spew ability. -->
  <Impid.description>Feito para a vida no deserto, as culturas de diabretes vivem em muitos mundos de borda e mundos de morte secos. Diabretes são extremamente rápidos, toleram facilmente altas temperaturas e podem cuspir fogo de suas bocas. Embora sejam mestres na areia, os diabretes lutam em outros ambientes. Eles são terríveis com a agricultura. Eles lutam bem à distância, mas em combate corpo a corpo sua fraqueza física se torna aparente.\n\nOs forasteiros os chamam de corredores de poeira por causa de sua velocidade em terreno aberto e resistência ao calor. Algumas tribos os chamam de demônios por causa de seus chifres e porque queimam seus inimigos. As táticas de combate das tribos de diabretes geralmente se concentram em ataques incendiários de abordagem rápida usando armas de fogo portáteis e sua capacidade de vomitar fogo.</Impid.description>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impids are very fast, can spew fire from their mouths, and easily tolerate high temperatures. They fight well at range, but in close combat they do little damage. They are terrible with farming, and have weak immune systems. -->
  <Impid.descriptionShort>Feitos para a vida no deserto, os diabretes são muito rápidos, podem vomitar fogo de suas bocas e toleram facilmente altas temperaturas. Eles lutam bem à distância, mas em combate corpo a corpo causam pouco dano. Eles são terríveis com a agricultura e têm sistemas imunológicos fracos.</Impid.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: neanderthal -->
  <Neanderthal.label>neandertal</Neanderthal.label>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. Their most salient characteristic is that they are difficult to hurt: They are very resistant to injury, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, without ever having evolved in a complex civilization, they are less adept than baseliner humans at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis was originally an archaic population of hominids that emerged over 200,000 years ago during the Pleistocene epoch. After they were replaced by and merged with humans 30,000 years ago, they were absent for tens of thousands of years until scientists resurrected them from ancient DNA. Neanderthals now survive in sub-societies on some settled planets. On the rimworlds, neanderthal tribes carve out the same existence as their Earth ancestors did so long ago. -->
  <Neanderthal.description>Os neandertais são humanóides atarracados e de constituição poderosa. Sua característica mais saliente é que eles são difíceis de machucar: eles são muito resistentes a lesões e seus fortes sistemas imunológicos os protegem de infecções. No entanto, sem nunca terem evoluído em uma civilização complexa, eles são menos hábeis do que os humanos padrão em tarefas intelectuais e sociais, e sua impulsividade pode torná-los perigosamente agressivos.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis era originalmente uma população arcaica de hominídeos que surgiu ao longo de 200.000 anos atrás, durante a época do Pleistoceno. Depois que eles foram substituídos e mesclados com humanos há 30.000 anos, eles ficaram inexistentes por dezenas de milhares de anos até que os cientistas os ressuscitaram através de DNA antigo. Os neandertais agora sobrevivem em subsociedades em alguns planetas estabelecidos. Nos mundos da borda, as tribos neandertais esculpem a mesma existência que seus ancestrais da Terra fizeram há muito tempo.</Neanderthal.description>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. They are hardy and difficult to injure, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, their minds are less adept at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive. -->
  <Neanderthal.descriptionShort>Os neandertais são humanóides atarracados e de constituição poderosa. Eles são resistentes e difíceis de ferir, e seu forte sistema imunológico os protege de infecções. No entanto, suas mentes são menos hábeis em tarefas intelectuais e sociais, e sua impulsividade pode torná-los perigosamente agressivos.</Neanderthal.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: pigskin -->
  <Pigskin.label>pele de porco</Pigskin.label>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids which are capable of two-legged movement, tool use, and speech, but which also retain many pig-like qualities. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands leave them at a disadvantage when attempting to precisely manipulate tools and objects. They don't see well at a distance, so pigskin gangs usually focus on close-range weapons. They also have a strong taste for explosives.\n\nPigskins were made for their organs. Uncomfortable with the idea of harvesting organs from baseliner humans, a long-gone government merged human DNA into pigs to make the animals produce more easily-transplantable hearts and lungs. They succeeded, but the resulting creatures became more humanlike than anyone anticipated. -->
  <Pigskin.description>Os peles de porco são híbridos de humanos e porcos que são capazes de se deslocar em duas pernas, usar ferramentas e falar, mas que também possuem muitas qualidades semelhantes a porcos. Eles são resistentes e podem comer quase tudo sem adoecer, mas suas mãos em forma de pata os deixam em desvantagem ao tentar manipular ferramentas e objetos com precisão. Eles não enxergam bem à distância, então grupos de peles de porco geralmente se concentram em utilizar armas de curto alcance. Eles também gostam muito de explosivos.\n\nPeles de porco foram produzidos por conta de seus órgãos. Desconfortável com a ideia de usar órgãos de humanos padrão, um governo antigo fundiu DNA humano em porcos para fazer com que os animais produzissem corações e pulmões mais facilmente transplantáveis. Eles conseguiram, mas as criaturas criadas se tornaram mais humanas do que qualquer um esperava.</Pigskin.description>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands are bad at fine manipulation. They don't see well at a distance, so they usually focus on close-range weapons. They have a strong taste for explosives. -->
  <Pigskin.descriptionShort>Os peles de porco são híbridos de humanos e porcos. Eles são resistentes e podem comer quase tudo sem ficar doente, mas suas mãos em forma de pata são ruins em manipulação refinada. Eles não enxergam bem à distância, então geralmente se concentram em armas de curto alcance. Eles têm um forte gosto por explosivos.</Pigskin.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: sanguophage -->
  <Sanguophage.label>sanguófago</Sanguophage.label>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are a type of archotech-enhanced xenohuman. Powered by archites, their abilities go far beyond normal genetic enhancements. They are mentally adept and preternaturally beautiful. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. They don't age or die naturally and never suffer from disease or poison. A sanguophage can make a new sanguophage by reimplanting their own xenogerm into a person.\n\nSanguophages must regularly consume hemogen derived from human blood, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light.\n\nThe first sanguophage appeared thousands of years ago when the lord-explorer Varan-Dur sought to control a hyperintelligent archotech and found himself transformed by it instead. Every sanguophage is descended from him. Since then, sanguophages have often been hunted because of their destabilizing power and their need for blood. Since they can pass for baseliners, many live in hiding among typical humans.\n\nTheir numbers are unknown. Some think they are legends or rare irrelevancies. Some believe sanguophages secretly direct entire human civilizations. The stories speak of eternal lords ruling billions from slate-black space stations, or directing blood sacrifices at conferences in the underlayers of the deepest urbworlds. -->
  <Sanguophage.description>Sanguófagos são um tipo de xenohumano aprimorado por aquotécnologia. Alimentado por arquitas, suas habilidades vão muito além dos aprimoramentos genéticos normais. Eles são mentalmente aptos e sobrenaturalmente bonitos. Em combate, eles podem lançar espinhos mortais e curar amigos feridos. Eles não envelhecem ou morrem naturalmente e nunca sofrem de doenças ou venenos. Um sanguófago pode fazer um novo sanguófago reimplantando seu próprio xenogerminador em uma pessoa.\n\nOs sanguófagos devem consumir regularmente hemogênio derivado de sangue humano e devem periodicamente realizar o descanso mortal por longos períodos. Eles são facilmente destruídos pelo fogo e desacelerados pela luz UV.\n\nO primeiro sanguófago apareceu há milhares de anos, quando o senhor-explorador Varan-Dur procurou controlar um arquotécnico hiperinteligente e se viu transformado por ele. Todo sanguófago é descendente dele. Desde então, os sanguófagos têm sido frequentemente caçados por causa de seu poder desestabilizador e de sua necessidade de sangue. Como eles podem se passar por humanos padrão, muitos vivem escondidos entre humanos típicos.\n\nSeus números são desconhecidos. Alguns pensam que eles são lendas ou raras irrelevâncias. Alguns acreditam que os sanguófagos dirigem secretamente civilizações humanas inteiras. As histórias falam de senhores eternos governando bilhões de estações espaciais pretas como ardósia, ou dirigindo sacrifícios de sangue em conferências nas camadas inferiores dos mundos urbanos mais profundos.</Sanguophage.description>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are ageless, deathless super-humans powered by archotech-created archites in the bloodstream. They are beautiful and extremely intelligent. They can heal any injury, and never suffer from disease or poison. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. The price is that sanguophages must consume hemogen derived from human blood to survive, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light. -->
  <Sanguophage.descriptionShort>Sanguófagos são super-humanos eternos e imortais, alimentados por arquitas, criados por arquotécnicos, na corrente sanguínea. Eles são lindos e extremamente inteligentes. Eles podem curar qualquer ferimento e nunca sofrem de doenças ou venenos. Em combate, eles podem lançar espinhos mortais e curar amigos feridos. O preço é que os sanguófagos devem consumir hemogênio derivado do sangue humano para sobreviver, e devem periodicamente realizar o descanso mortal por longos períodos. Eles são facilmente destruídos pelo fogo e desacelerados pela luz UV.</Sanguophage.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: waster -->
  <Waster.label>toxicadores</Waster.label>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo.\n\nOriginally engineered to prevent resettlement of post-apocalyptic deathworlds, wasters are living area-denial weapons. Waster pirates armed with toxic weapons are the bane of many frontier peoples, both on the rimworlds and in the depths of the urbworld hyperstructures. -->
  <Waster.description>Os toxicadores são agressivos, imunes à poluição tóxica, quase imunes a doenças e podem ingerir tanto psicoide e drogas de despertar quanto desejarem, sem efeitos nocivos. Seu metabolismo adaptado à toxina significa que eles devem consumir alguma forma de psicoide - geralmente as drogas floco ou brilho.\n\nOriginalmente projetados para evitar o reassentamento de mundos de morte pós-apocalípticos, os toxicadores são armas vivas de negação de área. Piratas toxicadores armados com armas tóxicas são a ruína de muitos povos da fronteira, tanto nos mundos da borda quanto nas profundezas das hiperestruturas dos mundos urbanos.</Waster.description>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo. -->
  <Waster.descriptionShort>Os toxicadores são agressivos, imunes à poluição tóxica, quase imunes a doenças e podem ingerir tanto psicoide e drogas de despertar quanto desejarem, sem efeitos nocivos. Seu metabolismo adaptado à toxina significa que eles devem consumir alguma forma de psicoide - geralmente as drogas floco ou brilho.</Waster.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: yttakin -->
  <Yttakin.label>yttakin</Yttakin.label>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments. Yttakin share a psychic connection with the wildlife and can summon animals to their side during battles. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before.\n\nSince they migrated off their icy birthworld of Yttak, Yttakin settlements live on many planets. Their fur, roaring voices, and aversion to urban living sometimes leads naive outsiders to believe they are simple-minded animals. Quick-minded Yttakin are happy to make good use of such wrong beliefs, whether at the negotiating table or on the battlefield. -->
  <Yttakin.description>Yttakin descendem de colonos projetados para prosperar em planetas ultra-frios. Seu grande tamanho e pelagem os tornam resistentes em ambientes congelados. Yttakin compartilha uma conexão psíquica com a vida selvagem e pode convocar animais ao seu lado durante as batalhas. Eles não são rápidos, enérgicos ou precisos, mas podem continuar quando outros teriam desmoronado muito antes.\n\nDesde que migraram de seu mundo gelado de Yttak, os assentamentos de Yttakin existem em muitos planetas. Sua pele, vozes de rugido e aversão à vida urbana às vezes levam pessoas de fora ingênuas a acreditar que são animais simplórios. Yttakin de mentes rápidas ficam felizes em fazer bom uso dessas crenças erradas, seja na mesa de negociações ou no campo de batalha.</Yttakin.description>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments, and they have a unique ability to communicate vocally and psychically with animals. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before. -->
  <Yttakin.descriptionShort>Yttakin descendem de colonos projetados para prosperar em planetas ultra-frios. Seu grande tamanho e pelagem os tornam resistentes em ambientes congelados, e eles têm uma capacidade única de se comunicar vocal e psiquicamente com os animais. Eles não são rápidos, enérgicos ou precisos, mas podem continuar quando outros teriam desmoronado muito antes.</Yttakin.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>