<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: Core -->
  <Core.label>Core</Core.label>
  <!-- EN: Core RimWorld content. -->
  <Core.description>Conteúdo principal do RimWorld.</Core.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Royalty -->
  <Royalty.label>Royalty</Royalty.label>
  <!-- EN: The Empire has arrived. Their honor-bound culture wields hyper-advanced technology, while bowing to the ancient traditions of kings, queens, titles and honor.\n\nEarn royal titles. Construct luxurious thronerooms and royal chambers. Call Imperial elite troops and bond with unique Imperial bladelink weapons.\n\nUse new psychic abilities. Blind, mind-control, nauseate, and induce insanity. Teleport, block pain, confer deadly focus, and turn invisible.\n\nServe the Imperial High Stellarch well and earn a pass off the rimworld.\n\nA new quest system procedurally generates unique quests, combining different goals, foes, guests, rewards, helpers, special threats, and world conditions. The expansion adds a large amount of new quest content.\n\nMechanoids can now create clusters of mechanoid buildings. Each mech cluster generates with a unique layout, presenting a unique tactical puzzle. Mech clusters always appear in an initially dormant state, so you can plan and execute a careful attack - or use them against your foes.\n\nYou don't have to serve the Empire. You can steal psychic amplifiers and other Imperial technology. The rebel life is free - but challenging.\n\nThis expansion includes a new album music by Alistair Lindsay, composer of the original RimWorld soundtrack. -->
  <Royalty.description>O Império chegou. Sua cultura ligada à honra possui uma tecnologia hiper-avançada, enquanto se curva às antigas tradições de reis, rainhas, títulos e honra.\n\nGanhe títulos reais. Construa luxuosas salas do trono e câmaras reais. Chame as tropas de elite Imperiais e se vincule com armas bladelink únicas do Império.\n\nUtilize novas habilidades psíquicas. Cegueira, controle mental, náusea e induzir insanidade. Teleporte, bloqueie a dor, e fique invisível.\n\nSirva bem ao Arquistelar Supremo Imperial e ganhe um passe para fora do rimworld.\n\nO novo sistema de missões gera continuamente missões únicas, combinando diferentes objetivos, inimigos, convidados, recompensas, ajudantes, ameaças especiais e condições mundiais. A expansão adiciona uma grande quantidade de novos conteúdos de missões.\n\nMecanoides agora podem criar aglomerados de construções mecanoides. Cada aglomerado mecanoide é gerado com um layout exclusivo, apresentando um quebra-cabeça tático exclusivo. Os aglomerados mecanoides sempre aparecem em um estado inicialmente inativo, para que você possa planejar e executar um ataque cuidadoso - ou usá-los contra seus inimigos.\n\nVocê não precisa servir o Império. Você pode roubar amplificadores psíquicos e outras tecnologias imperiais. A vida rebelde é livre - mas desafiadora.\n\nEsta expansão inclui um novo álbum de Alistair Lindsay, compositor da trilha sonora original do RimWorld.</Royalty.description>
  
</LanguageData>