<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<LanguageData>

  <Altar_Small.label>small altar</Altar_Small.label>
  <Altar_Small.description>A small platform that plays a role in ideoligious rituals.</Altar_Small.description>

  <Altar_Medium.label>medium altar</Altar_Medium.label>
  <Altar_Medium.description>A medium platform that plays a role in ideoligious rituals.</Altar_Medium.description>

  <Altar_Large.label>large altar</Altar_Large.label>
  <Altar_Large.description>A large platform that plays a role in ideoligious rituals.</Altar_Large.description>

  <Altar_Grand.label>grand altar</Altar_Grand.label>
  <Altar_Grand.description>A grand platform that plays a role in ideoligious rituals.</Altar_Grand.description>

  <Ideogram.label>ideogram</Ideogram.label>
  <Ideogram.description>A large image drawn on the ground and reinforced with metal edges. It is used as a focus for rituals.</Ideogram.description>

  <Darklamp.label>standing darklamp</Darklamp.label>
  <Darklamp.description>A low-powered electrical standing lamp that emits a dim light over a large area. People who prefer to work in darklight are happy with this light source.</Darklamp.description>

  <Darktorch.label>darktorch</Darktorch.label>
  <Darktorch.description>A specially-treated wooden torch that produces a dim light over a large area. People who prefer darklight work best with this light source. Can be automatically refueled with wood. Produces a small amount of heat.</Darktorch.description>

  <DarktorchFungus.label>fungus darktorch</DarktorchFungus.label>
  <DarktorchFungus.description>A specially-treated fungus torch that produces a dim light over a large area. People who prefer darklight work best with this light source. Can be automatically refueled with wood. Produces a small amount of heat.</DarktorchFungus.description>

  <SleepAccelerator.label>sleep accelerator</SleepAccelerator.label>
  <SleepAccelerator.description>A bedside device that accelerates the sleeper's circadian rhythm. This speeds up sleep, but consumes a lot of electricity and also causes increased hunger. It must be placed directly adjacent to and facing the head of the bed. Placing more than one sleep accelerator near the same bed has no effect.</SleepAccelerator.description>

  <BiosculpterPod.label>biosculpter pod</BiosculpterPod.label>
  <BiosculpterPod.description>An immersive pod equipped with a biosculpting fluid injector and attached control system. It can perform a variety of biological alterations including age reversal and pleasure-giving. Each pod becomes biotuned to its user, and cannot be used by anyone else. Biotuning resets after 60 days. Believers in transhumanism believe biosculpter pods are of critical importance in their quest to transcend normal human physical limitations.</BiosculpterPod.description>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.3.label>healing</BiosculpterPod.comps.3.label>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.3.description>Heal all fresh wounds and one random permanent injury.</BiosculpterPod.comps.3.description>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.4.label>age reversal</BiosculpterPod.comps.4.label>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.4.description>Reverse one year of aging.</BiosculpterPod.comps.4.description>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.5.label>pleasure</BiosculpterPod.comps.5.label>
  <BiosculpterPod.comps.5.description>Temporarily reshape the nervous system to deliver elevated levels of happiness for a time.</BiosculpterPod.comps.5.description>

  <NeuralSupercharger.label>neural supercharger</NeuralSupercharger.label>
  <NeuralSupercharger.description>A neuron-sensitizing device that can deliver one neural supercharge each day. A person with a neural supercharge will think and learn faster, but will also consume more food. The effect wears off in one day. Neural superchargers consume a lot of electricity.</NeuralSupercharger.description>
  <NeuralSupercharger.comps.2.jobString>Get neural supercharge</NeuralSupercharger.comps.2.jobString>


  <!-- Consumable buildings -->

  <ChristmasTree.label>christmas tree</ChristmasTree.label>
  <ChristmasTree.description>A celebratory tree decorated with ornaments and lights traditionally made as part of Christmas celebrations.</ChristmasTree.description>

  <CannibalPlatter.label>cannibal platter</CannibalPlatter.label>
  <CannibalPlatter.description>An area of floor covered with pre-chopped and arranged human meat ready for a cannibal feast.</CannibalPlatter.description>


  <!-- Burnable -->

  <Effigy.label>effigy</Effigy.label>
  <Effigy.description>A rough wooden frame in the shape of a human, ready to be burned as part of a ritual.</Effigy.description>

  <SacrificialFlag.label>sacrificial flag</SacrificialFlag.label>
  <SacrificialFlag.description>A flag representing enemies, ready to be burned as part of a ritual.</SacrificialFlag.description>

  <Pyre.label>pyre</Pyre.label>
  <Pyre.description>A wooden tower for ritual burning.</Pyre.description>


  <!-- Smoker -->

  <Burnbong.label>burnbong</Burnbong.label>
  <Burnbong.description>A wood structure packed with smokeleaf. It can be ignited during a ritual and produce a huge amount of smokeleaf smoke for a few hours, after which it is destroyed.</Burnbong.description>

  <IncenseShrine.label>incense shrine</IncenseShrine.label>
  <IncenseShrine.description>A collection of packed incense containers. It can be ignited and produce a powerful incense effect as a focus for rituals. It is destroyed after it burns down.</IncenseShrine.description>

  <RitualSpot.label>ritual spot</RitualSpot.label>
  <RitualSpot.description>A spot for carrying out certain kinds of rituals.</RitualSpot.description>


</LanguageData>