<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: starjack -->
  <Starjack.label>starjack</Starjack.label>
  <!-- EN: Engineered for life among the stars, starjack are built to withstand the unforgiving conditions of deep space living. Their reflective pressure-adaptive skin provides insulation against extreme temperatures and allows them to survive brief exposure to hard vacuum. These adaptations make them invaluable for spacewalk repairs and emergency decompression scenarios.\n\nMost starjack spend their lives beyond planetary gravity, leading to lower muscle mass and reduced physical strength compared to baseline humans. However, their resilience in zero-gravity environments makes them essential for maintaining orbital platforms and working aboard long-haul vessels.\n\nAs one of humanity's oldest xenotypes, starjack played a crucial role in the colonization of space. They are a common sight on deep-space stations and interstellar ships, where genetic modification is often a more cost-effective solution than upgrading spacecraft to support unaltered human physiology. -->
  <Starjack.description>Projetados para a vida entre as estrelas, os starjackes foram criados para suportar as condições implacáveis do espaço profundo. Sua pele refletiva e adaptativa à pressão oferece isolamento contra temperaturas extremas e permite sobreviver a exposições curtas ao vácuo. Essas adaptações os tornam indispensáveis para reparos fora da nave e cenários de descompressão de emergência.\n\nA maioria dos starjack passa a vida além da gravidade planetária, o que leva a menor massa muscular e força física reduzida em comparação com humanos básicos. No entanto, sua resistência em ambientes de gravidade zero os torna essenciais para a manutenção de plataformas orbitais e para o trabalho em naves de longa distância.\n\nComo um dos xenotipos mais antigos da humanidade, os starjack tiveram um papel crucial na colonização do espaço. Eles são presença comum em estações de espaço profundo e naves interestelares, onde a modificação genética costuma ser uma solução mais econômica do que adaptar espaçonaves para sustentar fisiologias humanas não modificadas.</Starjack.description>
  <!-- EN: Engineered for life among the stars, starjack are built to withstand the unforgiving conditions of deep space living. Their reflective pressure-adaptive skin provides insulation against extreme temperatures and allows them to survive brief exposure to hard vacuum. -->
  <Starjack.descriptionShort>Projetados para a vida entre as estrelas, os starjackes foram criados para suportar as condições implacáveis do espaço profundo. Sua pele refletiva, adaptável à pressão, isola contra temperaturas extremas e permite sobreviver a curtas exposições ao vácuo.</Starjack.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>